Okay, I guess that is live.
All right, we'll get started in a couple
minutes. I'm loud today. What's going
on?
All right, maybe that's more normal.
Oh, I got announcements, too.
All right,
let's get started. Couple quick
announcements before we start. First of
all, um
we aren't that far away from the
midterm. Uh, one thing to note about
that is if folks have any accommodation
requests, including DSP accommodations
or anything like that, um, please check
out the link to, uh, form we sent out in
the weekly announcements. Please, uh,
try to fill that out by, uh, Thursday.
And secondly, I guess, please read the
weekly announcements in general. um
that's going to have all the
announcements for the the week with
timelines and um only some of those
announcements are going to go out over
lecture. Those will be more complete.
Any
questions in general before we start
into a new topic today which is
reinforcement learning.
Okay,
I am gonna start out by upstaging myself
here.
with this applet.
Um, so today we're going to be talking
about reinforcement learning. Um, which
we briefly touched on last time when we
talked about solving an MDP like the
decision about which slot machine to
play when we didn't know the payoffs.
And that's really the essence of
reinforcement learning. You're in an
environment and we imagine that
environment to be a state space in which
you have actions. So the same familiar
abstraction we've had so far. And we
think of it like an MDP where those
actions may be non-deterministic. So
their outcomes may not be certain and
those actions come along with the
rewards. And your goal is not only to
act in a way that maximizes the sum of
discounted in general rewards, but to
learn to do so. And where reinforcement
learning is different than just taking
an MDP and running value iteration or
expect a maxax or any method that we
could use to think about the consequence
of our actions is that in reinforcement
learning we don't know what those
actions do until we try and we don't
know what states are good until we visit
them. And so that's going to really
bring us to the same mathematical
formalism but a very different approach
to how we have to go about interacting
with them. And what you see here uh in
this applet is a
um what you see here is a simulated
one-legged robot. And I will just it's
reward is forward motion. You can
already see some interesting things like
for example it actually has to move
backwards in order to move forwards.
Like in every
in every step that it takes there's a
little bit of like a lift backward. And
so it really isn't about just every
single step, but about the sum of those
rewards. And sometimes to go forward,
you have to go a tiny bit backward
because trigonometry. Um, and you can
see that it's it's learning. It's
already doing something. And we'll just
let that run in the background. And
we'll come back to that one at the end
of the um at the end of the lecture and
see how far it's gotten. All right. So
reinforcement learning the basic idea is
we now have agents and rather than
thinking about simulating
um look ahead and planning in a known
environment which is it's really a
really boils down to planning. We're
going to be focusing on the learning
aspect about basically this goes back
all the way to the earliest roots of
reinforcement learning um go back to uh
to studies of humans and behavioral
learning and the idea that you know like
for example if you want to you have a
dog and you want to train it you give it
a treat when it does the right thing and
uh eventually it learns uh to do that. I
um am going to show a quick video
sequence here because I find this
hysterical. These are not my cats. These
are um I believe Emma's cats. Uh but
here, so this is teaching a cat to play
fetch, which I find very different than
how you would do with a dog. So here um
she throws the ball and the cat takes
the ball away and the other cat's
wondering what's going on. Okay, so here
this is iteration two.
You throw the ball and the cat chases it
and
sort of pretends like you never saw
that.
And iteration three,
you throw the ball.
Yeah, cats aren't going to have it.
Okay, so in fact, this is a perfectly
good example of reinforcement learning,
which boils down to there was no actual
reward involved for the cats and they
learned to ignore the ball, which may
not have been what you wanted them to
learn. Um, but there's something to be
learned there about reinforcement
learning or maybe about cats. Anyway,
um, here's the setup and reinforcement
learning. We still have agents and
environments. That hasn't really changed
at any point here. The difference is now
we think really fundamentally about the
agent environment loop as opposed to
purely the structure of a model that we
already have of that environment. And so
in this case we have our agent taking
actions. So these symbols will all be
familiar. Um and in fact the whole setup
is in some sense familiar but the the
twist is very important. So in this case
we take actions. Those are the same
actions we had all along except now
instead of taking them in simulation we
actually take them in the environment.
As a result the environment is going to
reply to us. It's going to reply to us
by placing us in a resulting state. So,
we were in some state, we took some
action, and the environment places us in
a resulting state, S prime. Okay. Now,
you could wonder, wait, what if I can't
tell what my resulting state is? Maybe
what if I only have partial vision or
something like that. And that's actually
a very important setting, too, that
corresponds to a partially observable
markup decision process. We'll talk
about those much later in the course.
Um, but for now, the idea is you were in
some state S. And this is again, we're
thinking about the fully observable
case. So you know what state you're in.
You know what actions are available. You
take one. Maybe it was a bad idea, but
you take it. You end up receiving some
new state. Okay. Apparently when you
take action A in state S, you can land
in S prime. Is that always going to
happen? Is it rarely going to happen?
You're not really going to know until
you try it a bunch. Okay. But when you
take an action in a state, you land in a
result state and then you get an
instantaneous reward. And you need to
learn to act to maximize the sum or the
sum of discounted instantaneous rewards.
So that's sort of the core of it. We're
getting feedback in the term in terms of
the rewards. They're the same rewards or
costs we've had all along, but instead
of knowing them in advance, we get them
by trial and error. So that's going to
be a twist. And the utility just as
before with MDPs is just the reward
function. You're trying to maximize the
sum of rewards again generally with a
discount to define your horizon. And you
have to learn how to act to maximize
your expected rewards. Okay. All the
learning you get to do is based on these
observed samples. So you don't know what
action A does in state S. Well, now you
do, right? You just tried it. And that
means that in order to know what the
actions do, you have to visit states
that you haven't been before so that you
can try out the actions to see what
happens there. It also means you might
have to take actions multiple times
because this is non-deterministic. And
in general, unless you happen to know
you're in a deterministic setting,
you're going to have to try actions over
and over and slowly start to learn what
they do and how often. in the same way
that in the last lecture we didn't know
what the one slot machine paid off until
we pulled the lever a bunch of times.
And so issues like the statistical
concerns and the sampling issues are
going to be front and center. So let me
give you some more examples and then
we'll dive into um some actual
approaches we can do to do this. So here
is um these are this is from IBO soccer
um from a while back. This is Colon
Stone and the idea is it's robot soccer.
So, actually, I'll show you some robot
soccer uh videos later. These things are
adorable. But, um uh basically, you got
to get your eyeballs to play soccer. And
this is hard in a couple ways. First of
all, um the way you want to move to play
soccer optimally isn't sort of the
obvious mimic a real life dog with
straight legs. You kind of want more
support and so they kind of bend down
onto the elbows. So, how should you
position your body? How should you move?
And then even if you've already trained
to do this, you go to some new field and
maybe it's a little more worded down or
the material is different and it doesn't
work exactly the same way as what you u
might have available to you beforehand.
And so what you have to do is some
reinforcement learning, right? You know
your position, you know your actions. Um
but you don't really know how much your
legs are going to slip or how much the
robot is going to rock and things like
that until you try it. Okay? And now you
could think, wait a minute, isn't that
all physics? Couldn't I figure that all
out? And sometimes you can turn a
reinforcement learning problem into a
into a modeling solution problem, but
you got to know a lot. So, so you have
to know something and then it's only
going to be as good as your model. So,
sometimes people do hybrid things where
you start out in a simulation that is
your best guess as to how the world
works, but you still have to go to the
real world and polish things off. So,
here, let's take a look at um let's take
a look. This is a basically functional
walking. You can see it's kind of
slipping and it's not, you know, this is
not, this is not an Olympic ibo yet. Um,
but it's more or less moving forward,
which means it's more or less getting
rewards. And that's really powerful
because when you're getting rewards,
even if they're intermittent, you know
what you did that got those. You know,
oh, that time maybe my arm was a little
bit straighter and I went a little
further. And then you've learned
something. Okay? And as that goes on,
you can continue to modify what you do.
How do you do that? We're going to have
to talk about that. And you can see now
it's much more efficient during
training. And here is after the tuning
on this field. And now you can see how
it like lines up. It's ready to go.
Okay. So super efficient. And this sort
of optimizing something that's already
in basically the ballpark is one of the
places where reinforcement learning um
had its first successes. And it doesn't
just work in cases like this where we
more or less know how a quadriped should
move. Um though of course this is a very
simple if if you're walking around in
the woods it's much harder to know how
to move. Um we'll talk about this later
in in the course. You have to decide
things like where am I going to place my
foot and then how do I adjust to make
sure that all of the forces involved
don't involve slipping and things like
that. But you know, quadripeds, if you
go to something like here, this is um
here this is a
a side winder snake sort of motion where
it's much less obvious. There are a
bunch of joints in the snake and
figuring out how to move them all in
sequence uh kind of in the right pattern
so that all of the forces do the right
thing and end up with actual motion as
opposed to just thrashing around is
really hard. Like if somebody gave you
and said, "Hey, manually get this ibo to
walk forward." You could probably figure
that out. Like move the one leg, then
move the next. And you know, you could
probably sort that out. It'd be much
harder to sit down and write a script to
control all of the angles of all of um
the motors in this snake to get it to do
something like that. And then of course
uh I would be remiss if I did not
mention the crawler which we will be uh
uh doing in our project three. So, let's
check in on that crawler. Let's see how
we're doing. How are we doing?
So, here's the crawler. Uh, I can say a
little bit more about the crawler now,
which is already getting a little better
here. So, this crawler basically
controls two angles. The angle of where
the yellow arm meets the body. We could
call that the shoulder. And that it has
an action to move that up or down. Um
and then it can control how the red um
the red arm bends at the juncture with
the yellow arm and that it can increase
and decrease that angle. And so there's
some pattern of increasing and
decreasing those angles that will result
in this kind of scooping motion which
will move it and it's slowly discovering
that like I don't know how to control a
one- arm crawler but it's going to sort
it out. There's going to be some pattern
that works. Let's let's send that thing
back to school and let it keep going.
Okay. Um,
all right.
So, let's figure out how we could build
that crawler bot. We still have an MDP.
Okay. It's still markup decision pro uh
problem. Um, we still have a set of
states. We still have a set of actions.
And we still imagine that there is a
model of the transition dynamic. So, we
imagine that for any state s and any
action a prime, there's a distribution
over states s prime that can result.
There's still a reward function which is
for every transition you experience from
a state s an action A landing in S prime
there's a reward you get and we're still
looking for a policy that tells you in
each state what to do. For example, for
the crawler robot it might tell you that
when you're both angles are at 90° you
should actuate the you know the elbow in
the positive direction. That would be a
policy. Okay. So all of that is the same
as it was before. And so we imagine
there's still that MDP, but the new
twist is that we don't know uh T or R.
So we imagine they exist. Formerly
there's an MDP, but it's an unknown one.
So we don't know T. That means we don't
know what the actions do. So until we
get in a state and we take an action, we
don't know what other states it leads
to. Um and we also don't know R, which
means until we're in a state and we take
an action, we don't know whether there's
a big reward there. That means, for
example, in grid world where it was
always, oh, how do we arrange to get
ourselves to that big positive reward
reward in the corner? We don't know
until you go to the corner and pull the
exit lever. You don't know whether it's
a plus or a minus. Now, maybe you'll
figure that out really fast or maybe
you're going to need multiple tries to
do it, but that's that's sort of the new
twist here. You don't know T or R. And
so, you actually have to try out actions
and states to figure out uh what's good.
So,
all those transitions are gone until you
learn them. Okay. very important point
to distinguish everything we did with
MDPs to what we're going to be doing
from here on out with reinforcement
learning is the difference between the
offline setting and the online setting.
So in the offline setting with an MDP
you are in a world you know it's well
modeled by an MDP which you know and so
before you take any action to cross the
bridge or whatever you stop and you
think and you run value iteration or
whatever it is you're doing run expect a
maxax and you plan and you think and you
construct a policy consider the options
do whatever it is you're doing with the
MDP and then and only then after you've
done all that computation in simulation
hypothetically under your model you then
go and you execute your polic policy and
you know hopefully the model was close
enough to reality that executing that
policy performs well but you don't
actually jump into any pits. You just
imagine doing it and realize you
shouldn't and then you go along and
execute the policy that you determine to
be optimal. In the online case that is
not true. This is like the slot machine.
You can't tell if it has a good payout
until you put your money in and pull the
lever. And that means you are actually
experiencing these transitions. And
that's a big deal. For example, you want
to learn to fly fly a helicopter. It's
entirely possible you're going to crash
a bunch of helicopters. And so you have
to be really careful in what actions you
take and how you balance the
exploration, trying new things with
exploitation, doing things that result
in rewards. And starting next lecture,
we're going to talk about that balance
and what you do about the fact that this
is real action in the real world. But
for now, I just want to be clear that
today everything we do with
reinforcement learning, even though when
I show you an applet, it's still grid
world. It's still running some Python on
my machine, right? Um, today everything
is um showing the situation where you
are really taking the actions. And an
important point about really taking the
actions is you can't take them back. So
when we're doing search, you could have
this whole fringe or frontier of
unexplor sorry of um unexpanded nodes
and you could go back to them if your
plan didn't work out. You had a bunch of
backup things. Once you jump into the
fire, you can't like unjump into the
fire and try something new. You can't
rewind time here. Okay. And so that
means that it's a very different
setting.
In the majority of cases, we break up
our experiences into episodes, which is,
okay, you started here, you ran this
thing out, you fell into the pit. Okay,
next episode, and you're it's a new copy
of the robot, or you somebody comes and
resets you and picks the helicopter up
and untwists the blades or whatever it
is. Um, and so there's a sequence of
transitions you experience and they're
often broken into these um, episodes,
each one of which is a continuous
experience in the environment, but then
it ends and you need to be reset or
maybe there are multiple agents that are
experimenting at the same time. And so
you'll see that as well. Okay. All
right.
So when we are doing reinforcement
learning, there are two broad classes.
One is what's called modelbased
learning, which is is less frequently
done. Um the other one's called model
free learning which is more frequent.
We're going to do model based learning
because it directly uses what we already
know and then we're going to see how we
can approximate it with model free
learning. So model based learning which
is sort of an intermediate thing um says
all right well
and just to be clear neither is
inherently better. They both have
strengths and they both have weaknesses.
It just turns out in the real world
model free learning uh is more
widespread. So in modelbased learning
the idea is this. Well, if I knew the
MDP, I could solve it using techniques
from last week, and I don't know the
MDP. So, step one should be figure out
what MDP I'm living in. That means step
one is pull the lever on the slot
machine a bunch and figure out its
payouts. And then once you know that, do
what you would do to a known MDP. Okay?
So, you learn an approximate model based
on your experiences. and your
experiences go towards knowledge of a
transition model that you maintain and
do whatever uh learning you're going to
do and then once you have that you solve
your run value iteration do whatever
okay so step one involves learning an
empirical uh MDP and this can be super
simple so for each state s and action A
that you see
just count up all the S primes you land
in now this only really works if you
have seen state S and you've taken
action A from that state and you've done
it enough times to have a credible
estimate or picture of what happens. But
if we have a bunch of experiences of I
was in state S, I took action A and then
I saw S prime 1 and then the next time
that happened I saw S prime 2 and then
the next time it happened I saw S prime
3. And once we have a bunch of these, we
can say, "All right, well, I actually
know these five states are the ones that
occur, and here's how often they
happen." Will my outcomes be exhaustive?
You can never really know that. Will
your probabilities be exact? Definitely
not. And we could use some statistical
machinery to find out how far we think
we are. But basically, we um discover
what the actions do as we try them, and
we discover the rewards as we experience
them. So over time, we'll have a
reasonable empirical. The hat here means
empirical. We'll have an empirical
estimate of the transitions, an
empirical estimate of the rewards, and
then we can go ahead and solve that.
We'll of course be solving the wrong
MDP, but it was a model anyway, and we
know how to solve it. So, we could use
value iteration or expect search or
whatever we like. Okay, so let's do an
example of this and that will lead us to
um this will lead us to a couple ideas
which will slowly get us to uh the core
reinforcement learning algorithms. And
there's a couple pieces that we're going
to have to put together. Um, and at the
beginning, I'm just going to show you
the simplest case. Okay, the idea is
here's the policy. All right, so this is
what we're going to do. We're not
learning a policy. We're just given a
policy to follow. And or you could also
imagine we're watching an agent follow
this policy. We may think it's a
terrible policy, but we're taking notes
while the agent does it. And we're going
to try to learn based on the experiences
that unroll. Okay, so we imagine this is
our policy. We imagine that we are
assuming the discount to be one to
simplify things and we run an agent
through this grid world four times.
Well, when I look at this, I don't
really first of all, the agent wouldn't
necessarily even know it's connected in
this way. We're doing a lot of visual
processing and we know that like the the
east action tends to move you to the
right and so on, but all you would
actually have to work work on is these
observed episodes that you would see in
training. And so we look at this and we
think, well, okay, well, what does what
actually happens? Well, if we want to
solve the MDP, we got to start doing the
work of knowing the transition. So, for
example, we would like to know from B,
which seems to be our start state. We
would like to know if you take the east
action,
what happens? Well, we could ask
apparently you can end up in C. So, B
east C um which is the probability of C
given B and east. Okay. Well, how often
did that happen? Well, B east led to C
here. here.
Okay, I guess that's it. So that's one,
right? Probability one. Is that truly
what it does? Probably not. But that's
what happens in our data. So we could
put a little hat here to say empirical.
Let's find out another one. C
east.
How what is the likelihood when you're
in C and you go east that you land in
state D? That's the probability of D
given C and the action east. Well, we
look and we say, well, C east led to D
here and it led to D here and it led to
D here, but then it led to A here. So,
you know, three quarters
and we could continue this way. Let me
PowerPoint all that. We could this way
and learn our model. And similarly, we'd
learn some rewards like we know that
going east from D gives you negative 1.
Uh the east from C landing in D gives
you negative 1. That tells us this
entry. And there was this time when we
took exit from D, we landed in the
terminal state and got plus 10. So now
we know that there's a plus 10 there.
And as we assemble this, we have a
model. Is it right? It's not. It's not
right. The transitions are all wrong. Um
because the rewards are deterministic
once you see them they're in fact right.
And we could solve this one. And we
could worry about if it's a little off,
how off is the resulting solution. So we
could worry about like are the errors
going to amplify or is this a pretty
robust process? But that's the general
idea. learn the learn learn learn this
uh learn what all the transitions do by
experience. There's some serious issues
with this.
What are some issues you can see with
going about this approach?
Okay. So there's certainly like the
normal statistical concerns of if I have
a small number of things the estimates
are going to be off and you know really
for a very long time I'll have
meaningful uncertainty in those those
estimates. Uh that's is a particularly
bad if there's a lot of states. You got
to try them all. Okay. What else?
Okay. There's some other big problems
here. Like what about the states you
never get to with this policy, right?
You don't know what they do. So, you
would need to somehow make sure that the
experiences you're watching cover
everything. Well, what if they don't?
There's just going to be huge chunks you
just don't know anything about. What
other problems would we have here? Well,
there's this problem that um we actually
are experiencing these things in the
real world and so like we actually
receive that negative 10. That could be
bad, you know? Uh and so sometimes
that's that's fine. like you play a
bunch of you play a bunch of games and
it's fine. But you know once you're like
crashing a model helicopter maybe that's
bad if you're trying to teach drones to
fly or something like that. Okay, what
other problems? Well, one problem is
let's say you decided you're like hey it
seems like really really important that
we understand what actions do from C. So
let's gather a bunch of examples of what
actions do in C. Well, how do you do
that? You got to get to C and try them.
Well, how do you get to C? I don't know.
Right? This doesn't really tell you how
to get more observations of a state and
an action. It just tells you how to
learn about them as they flow in. So,
there's a big piece here that's going to
be missing about how to actually
experience the things you need to
experience in order to uh learn what you
need to learn. All right. So, any
questions on modelbased learning? You
watch experiences, you estimate the MDP
from it, you solve that MDP, and you run
with that.
Okay. All right.
Let's do an example of a structurally
trivial but a reinforcement learning
problem. I would like to compute the
expected age, the average age of CS188
students. Okay, how could I do that?
Well, if I happen to know how likely you
were to be every age, I would just do
the math. I would take every age a I
would multiply it by the fraction of
people that have that age and I would
sum them up. It would be a weighted
average. Okay, easy, right? So like
maybe a 35% or 20 or whatever it is and
I add them all up.
Okay, simple, right?
H when I do this,
I don't have to actually ask anyone
their age. I don't have to learn
anything. I'm just deriving a quantity
from my model. In this case, P of A is
my model, right? I'm deriving a quantity
from it. In this case, the expectation
that is equivalent to solving NMDP. But
if you don't have a model, you got to
learn a model or something like that.
And so the modelbased way to figure out
the expected age would be to say, all
right, I know how to take averages when
I know the distribution over ages. So
step one is I'm going to find the
distribution of ages, and I'm going to
have to do that by sampling. So, I'm
going be like, "How old are you? How old
are you? How old are you?" And I'm going
to get a bunch of samples back. And
that's model based learning. I take my
samples. I estimate the distribution
over ages from those samples. One way to
do that is to just use the relative
frequency estimators, which are the
maximum likelihood estimators for um for
that data. There might be fancier things
we could talk about doing, but for this
example, and then once I've finished
learning this distribution, I just go
back and I do them the thing that I did
before, which is I know how to compute
an expectation. Now, in this case, an
expectation is a simple thing, but the
expectation is a proxy for solve the MDP
or whatever you wanted to do with your
model. What else could you even do other
than learn the model P of A and then go
and compute your expectation? What else
could we do?
Well, first of all, why does this even
work? This works because if we do this
long enough um and we take enough
samples, you'll eventually learn the
right model and once you have the right
model, you'll, you know, solve the
expectation correctly. Okay, what else
could we do? The other idea, which in
this example may feel like nearly the
same thing, but it's not. The other
thing you could do is the model free
approach. You could say, all right,
again, I don't know P of A, but I'm also
not going to compute it. I'm just going
to directly compute the thing I care
about which is the expectation. And
there I say, how old are you? How old
are you? How old are you? And maybe a
bunch of people say 20. And what I do is
I take an average as I go. So I average
all the responses I get. That will also
converge to the expectation. And the
reason this works is because if there
are bunch of people who are at a certain
age, I'll get that answer frequently and
it will show up in the sum frequently.
So here I'm taking an unweighted average
and the fact that some ages are more
common than others will be reflected in
their occurring more often in my samples
and so I don't need to do I don't need
to access in my computations the weights
just some come into my average more and
some come in less and you end up with
the same expectation. Okay, it's a
simple case but like I it's good to be
really clear about this. On the right, I
am computing an average where some
things occur more and some things occur
less and they fold into the average in
the right proportions. And so I can use
unweighted an unweed average and I don't
need to explicitly ever construct the
model. I can just take the average as I
go. Okay, any questions on that? That's
like the key idea here is that you don't
need the model to compute averages. You
can just average the things as they come
in. And the fact that certain ages in
this case are more common in the model
will cause them to be reflected more in
your experiences. That's model free
learning.
Okay. All right. Let's talk about how we
can do reinforcement learning like that.
Well, so in model free learning, we
basically just try things and instead of
accumulating our experiences and then
stopping later and building a model from
them, which is model based learning,
it's totally legit. Instead, what we're
going to do is we're just going to like
take average as we go. You want to know
how well this this um this slot machine
pays off, you're just going to pay
you're just going to play it and average
as you go. And if it's lucky, like I
don't know what that means. If the
probability of a high payoff is high,
you'll just get a high average. You
won't need to ever compute the
probability of the payoff. The average
will just be right from your experience.
Okay. Um, we're going to start with a
case called passive reinforcement
learning. And the idea here is we're
going to simplify things in actually two
ways. One is we're not going to worry
about action selection. Remember we
talked before about if you want to
reinforcement, learn about the world,
you're gonna have to try things. Like if
you want to know, if you want to learn
to go to the best restaurant, you're
gonna have to try a bunch of
restaurants, including the ones that
aren't very good, because you won't know
until you go. Okay? And that sort of
active decisionmaking about what actions
to take for exploration is very
important and also very Thursday. Um, so
one is we're just going to be watching
some agent doing things and we're just
taking notes and trying to learn. So
it's passive. The other thing is we're
going to imagine that the policy is
fixed. So the specific thing we're going
to do is policy evaluation. If you
remember that from last time, in policy
evaluation, you have a fixed policy and
we are learning the values of the
states. But we're learning the thing we
called vi of the states. That is the
average return from that state under
this policy. We are not going to try to
learn the optimal values because
we'll do that soon. Um, but for now
we're imagining it's a fixed policy.
We're evaluating that policy and we
don't know the transitions of the
rewards, but we're going to try to get
by just with experiencing them. Okay?
So, the learner is along for the ride.
It's not making choices about what to
do. Um, you're just executing the
policy. We're learning from the
experience. We are not planning offline.
We're actually taking actions in the
world. We're also not evaluating the
optimal actions. We're just going to
evaluate how good things are from pi.
And because of these simplifications,
this actually makes the job really easy
for us. And as we lift these
restrictions, that will help us build up
to our core algorithms for reinforcement
learning. So again, the goal is to
compute values v pi for a state under
pi. So that's why there's a pi up here
in the superscript. And the idea is
really simple. We're just going to
average together the sample values. Um,
and in the simplest version of this,
like it could not be simpler. We're just
going to act according to pi. And every
time you visit a state, you write down
what happened from that state on. So
this time I was in this state and by the
end of the game I had received 10
points. Oh, I was in that state again,
but this time I received four points.
And if that's your whole experience is
that from this state under this policy
you've seen 10 and you've seen four, you
say, I guess the average is seven.
Okay, that's it. Average the ones you
get. It's called direct evaluation. It's
uh it's actually a pretty bad idea, but
but it's simple and in the limit of
infinite everything, it will work fine.
All right, so let's imagine here's our
policy and then we observe some
episodes. So, um let's say we train and
we see episode one, which is we were in
B. So, I guess follow on as best you can
with the this because it'll make more
sense if it's all grounded. In B, we
chose east and we ended up in C. Maybe
that won't happen next time, but that's
what happened here. From C, we chose
east and we end up in D. From D, we
chose exit. The game ended and we
received 10 points. Great. If I had to
right now tell you the value of B under
this policy, what would you say?
Okay, good quiz. What is the value of B
appear to be under this policy from this
admittedly single sample?
So discount is one. So you don't have to
worry about that. The value is a sum of
rewards. So it's not negative one. Okay,
it's not what happens next from B. It's
not plus 10. It's not the thing that
happens at the end. It is the sum. So
it's eight. All right. So if I had to
stop right now, I would say this thing
has a value of eight. D has a value of
10. And C has a value of nine. And
like that's more or less the algorithm
except we're going to average them when
there's multiple. So here's another
here's another episode and another
episode and another episode. And now we
want to figure out what the values are
under this. And so for example, we could
ask what's the value of A? So we look
and we say when have I been in A? Well,
only this one time. And under this
policy, I got -10 from there. And that's
my estimate. And then I see, okay, well
um
um what was the value at B? Well, here I
was at B and what did I get? I got
eight. Oh, I was in B again. What did I
get there?
Eight again. All right. So B is going to
be plus 8.
How about C? This is probably the most
important one to understand.
What value do I get from C? Well, how
many times have I been in C? Once,
twice,
thrice,
four times.
What did I get? Well, this first time I
got
nine. The second time I got nine. The
third time I got nine. But the fourth
time I got1.
All right. So empirically
the value so the average discounted
rewards the discount is one here. So
that doesn't really make a difference.
The average rewards from C is a quarter
* 9 plus a quarter* 9 plus a quart 9
plus a quart 9 plus a/4 *1 which is + 4.
Okay, does that make sense? C has a
lower value because unlike B where all
of the episodes from B ended up at the
good state, there was an episode that
moved through C that ended up in the
pit. Okay, so it has a lower value. And
we can keep doing this. Uh there's only
one left. Um I guess she left. So plus
10 over there, minus two there. All
right,
first of all, any questions on this?
No one ever does this. We'll talk about
why, but I want to make sure that it's
clear how it would work. Run a lot of
episodes. From each point, you just
compute the observed forward rewards and
average them. All right. Um,
what's good about this? It's easy to
understand. And did you see we didn't
need to know what TR were, right? Um,
they're kind of embedded in what you
experienced. So, this is going to
converge to the right thing eventually.
Um, and it just kind of computes the
correct averages using the samples in
the same way that just asking people how
old they are and averaging them
gives you the answer as if you knew
exactly how many people had that age and
computed the expectation. All right. So,
what's bad about this approach? Does
anybody see anything kind of disturbing
here?
Okay, so definitely there's a small
sample issue that when if you get
unlucky or just the variance in general
from taking samples here can cause
problems. So for example, E had a bad
experience, B had a good experience, but
they're like we actually know in this
MDP they're the same. Just it happens to
be in those training ones. the one that
started at the ones that started at B
happened to end in the good pip, but the
one that uh ones that started in D were
50/50. Okay, so that's just noise, but
it's ended up shaping these numbers kind
of to look like the samples. Okay,
that's a problem. Sure, that's basically
the
you need lots of samples to really know
things problem. What else?
Well, how could we have done better?
Well, I just said part of it, which is
we kind of know B and E are the same,
right? And so they probably, if you knew
something about this, you'd be like, you
know what, I don't really know the
transitions, the rewards either, but
there's a kind of symmetry to this
problem. I think B and E are basically
the same thing. Um, and you would be
suspicious of this. And maybe that would
lead you to a better algorithm. Like
maybe B and E should be pulled together
in some way. And if you think about
this, that is going to lead you to a
better algorithm. Okay, so what's bad
about this is it wastes all the
information about how the states are
connected. For example, what do we know
about B? We know that it leads to C
under this policy like every time,
right? Like B always leads to C and E
also always leads to C. So they do the
same thing. They both always lead to C.
How could they have different values?
Okay, so it's going to take a long time
to learn because we are not leveraging
information about what the states led
to. We're only leveraging information
about how it unrolled, which has a whole
bunch of extra variance, which is
irrelevant. Once you know that you once
you know that B takes you to C and E
takes you to C, it kind of doesn't
matter what happened from C onwards.
That should be pulled together. All
information about C should inform B and
E equally. But we're not doing that. So,
we're getting all this extra variance
that's making it that much harder to get
enough data to learn. Okay. Um,
actually, let me stop there for a
second. Any questions on that?
>> Yep.
>> Okay. Um, so in this case, all the
information about B comes from your
experiences from B. And if you've never
been to E, you'll learn nothing at all
about it. Okay, so that that seems
pretty clear. If you've never been
there, you have no idea what it does.
But if you've been to B many many times
and you go through and you go to C and
you tend to go to D and everything's
nice and then you go to E a couple times
and all you manage to learn as it leads
to C, you're actually pretty much there
because you know what C does. And
because you don't have that, each state
is kind of learning at its own rate. You
have to learn that whole future of the
game about every state as opposed to
only needing to learn a little horizon.
what does the state in action do? And
then you can connect it up to your other
learnings. So that that's the problem
here.
All right.
So let's go back. We actually what were
we computing? We were computing vpi of a
state. And we have an algorithm for that
already. We have this Bellman update. we
have we called it um we called it policy
evaluation which will compute for us
if we had the MDP this will compute
without any of those worries about the
statistics so let's just remember back
to um what we had last class for
computing the same quantity and the idea
then was well we'd like to compute the
value under pi for the state s and that
projects this little simplified tree
where you don't have a max you don't
have a choice of actions you're going to
do whatever pi tells you, but then
you're going to take an average over the
outcomes over the different s primes
that can result. And so we had an we had
a we had a dynamic program for that
where we would say that if we consider
the next zero rewards, the value under
pi is zero. And if we consider the next
k plus one rewards in terms of reward um
steps, then we could compute this
recursively. Okay, let's remember how
that was. You would say if I want to
know how what my score is going to be
like from state s under pi for k plus
one more rewards well I have to consider
all the things that could happen. So
there's going to be an average over um
all of the resulting s primes
and we have to average over according to
the probabilities which we don't know
but that's what we did before. So we
don't so this is our first problem. We
don't know these probabilities that's
why we can't use it. And then there's
some utility of ending up in S- prime
which was R the instantaneous reward
plus the kstep reward from our landing
state. Okay. And we also don't know that
but that was a problem before and we
solved it. We solved it by computing
this recursively and the and in
particular we solved it by um saying
that the VK + one the new estimate of
the value was based on the old estimate
of the value. Okay, so we managed to
break our way out of that. Um and then
of course we needed to be able to take
that average. Okay, so this approach was
much better on the grounds of dealing
with state connectivity because as soon
as we know that S leads to S prime, we
were then plugging in vi at S prime.
Okay, so this uh policy evaluation did
exploit the structure by reducing
everything to a one-step look ahead, a
one-step expect of some kind. So that's
what we want to do here. We'd like to do
policy evaluation in a reinforcement
learning setting and get the same effect
that we learn about a value from the
next state's value, not from the whole
game. And that we can do. The problem
here is although it exploited those
connections, we needed TNR to do it. So
the key question in reinforcement
learning is when can we do a Bellman
update? When can we do an update like
this that we know will converge to the
right quantity? When can we do it
without knowing the weights? And we've
actually only got one tool and that is
to replace averages which require a
model with samples which do not. So
we're going to look at this exact update
here and we're going to do it except
instead of taking an average we're going
to just take samples as we go and that's
going to be the basic idea not only for
this but for every algorithm we do in
reinforcement learning. So let's go back
and let's figure out how we can do that.
We'd like in policy evaluation to in be
computing values of states under the
policy.
In um in the known MDP dynamic
programming case, we did this in this
big batch process where we compute a
kstep approximation and use that to
compute a k + one step approximation.
But forget what these approximations
are. What they're really saying is the
old value at um at S prime is combined
with one step
to give us a new value
at well a different state. Okay, so the
new value at S gets combined with a
one-step experience and an old value a
step further in the future to improve
our estimate. And that's actually
something we can do. We can't take this
average, but we can um do it in a
different way. If we are an S and we
take this action, we can see where we
land and we can approximate this average
with just this one experience. So let's
see how that's going to work. So here
again we have the same little tree. We
imagine that we are sitting in um we are
imagine that we're sitting in state S.
Okay. And we'd like to be able to
compute this average up here
according to this equation. And let's
imagine we get samples of it. So instead
of actually computing the average, which
we can't do, we're going to collect
samples of the average and mash them all
together. Okay, so the first sample is
we were in state S, we took the required
action, we landed in the in S1 prime,
and then we have our old estimate at S1.
Then we have another sample again. We're
in the state, we're in this um we take
this action, we land somewhere else, and
then we have a forward estimate from the
new landing state. And so on and so on.
And this is just like the the case of
taking the average. We have these now
three or in general we're going to have
n samples.
Okay. And we can just average them
together. We can say that the new
estimate is just going to be the
unweighted average of these samples.
Okay. Why is that the same as taking the
actual weighted average? It's because if
a certain state is likely, it'll appear
many times in the average. and its
frequency of appearance in the long run
will match its probability. So if we
take samples of the experience out of s
pi of s and average them together, we
will accomplish this bellman update and
therefore learn the right thing.
All right,
big problem. What's the big problem?
This is actually everything I've written
here is right. You can replace that
weighted average with an unweighted
average of samples of the thing you're
averaging because the frequency of
things in the samples reflects the
weights that you would have applied
otherwise. So that's all true.
What's the flaw? We're so close to an
algorithm that we that will bust this
all open. But
>> I'm sorry.
>> Oh, it's a good question. Do we know R?
Um, you don't know R. But as soon as you
have a transition, you get R. So we are
getting them as we need them for this
purpose. It's a good question.
So I'm focusing on T, but R is also
unknown. It's just a it's kind of it's
less of a problem because it always
shows up in your experiences when you
need it. Okay, here's the problem. The
problem is we actually this is a
perfectly good algorithm, but it's these
samples of results from S P of S. You
can't arrange for 50 of them to come in
because they all come from S. And once
you take pi of S, you land in S prime
and you're you're like off to the races.
You can't rewind time and get another
sample. So you would have to sit and you
would have to wait until someday you
find yourself back at S and then you can
get your second sample. And in the
meantime, you're not learning. So the
problem here isn't that it doesn't work,
it's that the samples don't kind of come
in all at once. They're coming in one
sample here, one sample there, all over
the map, all over the different states.
Everything's kind of trickling you
samples in based on some pattern that
you can't control. And so we got to do
this, but we got to do it with one
sample and move on. Okay. And so that's
basically the problem is we um we can't
rewind time and get sample after sample
from that same state. So all right, so
until somebody gives us the ability to
do a crystal ball, which by the way we
have in offline planning, but um until
we have that, we're going to have to do
something else. And here um the key idea
is something called temporal difference
learning where we are going to learn
from every experience. But we're not
going to take a bunch of samples and
average them together. We're just going
to take every single sample we get in
and roll it in as like roll it in right
then and move on to a new state. So it
looks like this. We're going to learn
from every experience. We're going to
update the values every experience.
So a transition is I was in S. Action A
was taken. I landed in S prime and I
received reward R. Okay, if S is very
likely from SA, it'll contribute more
often in the long run. If it's unlikely,
it'll contribute less. So, we can just
average these things with equal weight,
but we only get one of them at a time.
So, what are we going to do? Okay, in
temporal uh first of all, just to be
clear on what we're doing, we're doing
temporal difference learning of values
right now. The policy is still fixed.
We're still evaluating the values under
this policy. And what we're going to do
is we're going to move the values
towards this experience and take a
running average. That's really the key
idea is a running average. So we get
this sample of V of S. So what's the
situation? We were in S here. We were
trying to compute V pi of S which is the
long-term rewards from S under this
policy. We see a sample which means we
happen to experience this transition
which landed us in S prime and gave us
reward uh R of S pi of S S prime. Okay.
So we have one sample. Well, now what
are we going to do? we need to do an
update to v pi of s.
Well, there's actually not a lot of
things we could do. On one hand, we have
our old estimate of v pi of s. So you've
got v pi of s as it's currently
estimated. It could be wildly wrong, but
you've got some estimate and then you've
got one sample. So you've got this on
one hand and you've got this on the
other hand. Your old estimate, your one
sample. Well, what are you going to do?
Before we took a bunch of samples and
clobbered the old estimate. We can't
afford to do that because this sample is
some real good learning um information,
but it's real, but it's sparse. It's
just a single sample. The old estimate
has all our memory of everything that's
happened so far, but it's out of date.
And so, we're going to blend them
together, and we're going to do it in
the simplest possible way, which is to
average them according to some weight.
So the update we're going to get is that
the new value of our estimate s is
mostly our old value of the estimate but
with the sample balanced in in this this
uh linear combination. And so alpha
might be um is alpha is a learning rate.
It might be 0.1 let's say and in that
case we're taking 0.9 of our old value
and 0.1 of our new value. It might be
0.5 and then it's 50/50. That'd be much
faster learning and there's a trade-off.
you learn to set alpha too small and you
don't it takes forever to learn. You set
alpha too too high and the noise in the
samples is going to overwhelm uh is
going to overwhelm things. Okay, that
same update is often written like this
that the new value is the old value plus
the learning rate times the difference
between the sample you got and the old
value. If this looks like a gradient
update, it should. This is saying take
your current value push it in the
direction of the observed error
or opposite of that I mean um with a
certain step size alpha. So remember um
for today I think it's probably most
useful to think of this taking a running
average for the future of the class you
should think about this as moving from
your current step in a direction um
given to you by this uh this gradient
with a sample and the current values
difference. Okay. So what does this do?
This gives you an average, right? If I
unroll this, if I take, let's say I take
um 0.9 of the current value and 0.1 of
the sample, what happens when the second
sample comes in 17 steps from now? Well,
now I'll have 0.1 of that new sample
and kind of 0.1 of the old sample, but
it's actually 0.9 of the old sample and
then 0.9 squared of the old value and so
on. And I'll start accumulating these
things um in in terms of this running
interpolation. So whenever we're taking
an average by saying the new s the new
average is the old average time 1 -
alpha plus this new sample time alpha
recent samples are going to be upweed
and so you're going to get that this
average is a mixture of all the samples
you've ever seen. That's good. That's
what we're hoping to accomplish is to be
able to mix these samples together even
though they're coming in at all kinds of
different times and erratically.
We have paid a little bit of a price
which is that the newer ones are
upweighted.
Okay. the smaller you make alpha, maybe
the less of a deal that's going to be.
All right, so that's the good news. This
sort of rolling in one sample at a time
and then coming back whenever we return
to that to there. Um the good news is
this gives us a running interpolation.
It kind of accomplishes the average in
the right way and we can prove this does
converge under the right conditions. um
we have what looks like a downside which
is that the more recent samples are
weighted more highly because everything
else is being decayed by one minus
alpha.
But that's actually kind of an advantage
because if you think about how value
iteration or any other algorithm like
this is going to work is that those old
samples
were actually kind of out of date
because they don't reflect all of the
learning that's happened since. So you
kind of want to decay them anyway. Okay,
so this is actually the behavior you
want. You forget about the past but
slowly. Um, if you decrease learning
rate alpha, this will eventually give
you like this will converge to the right
thing. All right, let's do an example
and then we'll see how to get beyond
what we've been solving because let's
remember what we've been solving so far
is how to estimate the value of a state
under a fixed policy which we had an
algorithm for immediately which is just
keep track of every time you're in that
state and average them together. This
algorithm is better because it combines
information from lots of different runs
based on how the states states are
connected. But it doesn't really change
the fact that we didn't we don't really
generally want to know the value under a
certain policy. We generally want to
know the optimal values. And even more
than that, we want to know the optimal
policy. So we kind of neither want the
value like like we neither want V nor
pi. We want pi star. And how are we
going to get there? So we need a couple
ideas to get there. But really
understanding this algorithm is going to
make it a lot easier uh to do the rest.
Okay,
let's do some temporal difference
learning. I'll do this one here because
we can do it in our heads and then we'll
do an example um once we have the next
layer of this algorithm. I'll do it in
the applet because then it becomes kind
of too much to work through the
examples. All right. So for here, let's
imagine these are our states. We're
imagining the discount is one and our
learning rate is 1/ half to keep things
simple. That is a very fast learning
rate. Okay. Um
let's imagine that this is our current
state. We currently believe that all the
states have value uh zero under this
policy. Um and except for that one state
that has value eight. Well, what does
that mean? That means that I think that
if I play the game a bunch of times from
here, I'll get an average summed reward
of zero. But if I played the game from
that exit square at D, I would get an
average of eight. So let's do something.
You got to observe things in order to
learn. So let's observe a transition. We
observe the transition. Well, we're in
B. Apparently the policy says to go
east, so that's what happens. And we
observe that we land in C. Great. And we
get a living reward in this case of -2.
Okay. Well, let's stop and think about
what we should believe after this. This
is where we are. We're now in C. Um, and
we receive this reward of uh -2. And so
we're going to do a computation. Now,
what can we learn about? The only thing
we can really learn about is the state
we were in. We can't really learn about
the state we landed in. We're here, but
we haven't done anything. So, we're not
going to learn anything about C by
arriving at C, right? The only thing we
can learn about is the state we left
because we just got this negative -2,
which should tell us something. But it
tells us something about about B, not C.
So, when we do this, this is actually an
important point that a lot of people
will confuse. You kind of leave learning
in your wake. you learn about the state
you left, not the one you arrive. Okay,
so let's take a look. Well, before we
had this estimate that vi of a was zero.
So we thought that our score was going
to be zero. All right, so let's write
that down. We thought our total score
was going to be zero. But we just took
this transition. And
what is what is what is this transition
telling us? This transition is telling
us that it seems like this time we're
going to get -2 because we just got that
plus
whatever is going to happen from C.
Well, what do we think is going to
happen from C? Well, zero. That's our
old estimate. So, before we took this
experience, we thought that B was going
to be worth zero on average. This turn
is looking like it's going to work out
to be -2. What do we do? We average them
together. In this case um we it's an
equal weighted average. So it is one
minus alpha which in this case is 02 of
our old value and then our new value
which is the instantaneous reward plus
our old estimate of the landing states
value and we're going to average them
together which will give us minus one.
And that means over here we're going to
say now I think the new value here is
minus one. Sorry uh the new minus the
value here is minus one. Let's first
check and make sure this made sense.
Does it make sense that a that um Okay,
also this was wrong. This is I don't
know why I wrote a there. That was B.
Okay. Does this make sense? Um it should
make sense because we used to think that
B was worth zero, but we just got -2 and
landed at a state that's worth zero.
That's worse than we thought. Maybe
we're unlucky, but we should make our
average go lower. So, that was the right
thing. Does it make sense that B is what
we updated? Sure. We just had a bad
experience leaving B. We don't know
anything about C that we didn't know
before. So hopefully it makes sense that
this value went down. Hopefully it makes
sense that B is what we learned about.
And the key thing is we were able to do
this update right now. We don't need to
know what happens in the future. We know
we got sent to C. And that's why this is
better than the direct evaluation we did
in the first place. Okay. All right. So
the new value, let me clean this up in
the PowerPoint so you can see it. The
new value at B is just going to be an
average of those two things, which is
negative one. Okay.
So if we keep doing this, you know,
we'll receive another value. So in this
case, uh the next transition we see is
from C, we choose east. That's what the
policy says. And we land in D. We
receive -2. Okay. So we would sort of
continue on with this. Now we know we're
in D. And we know we just received -2.
And we what are we going to update?
We're going to update a new value for um
for C because C looked like zero but it
just took us to D which is a good state.
Okay. So now we look on one hand we used
to think that the value under pi of C
was zero. And now we think on this
sample at least we think we're going to
get minus2 that we just received plus
the discounted value from D. The
discount is one and the value from D we
think is eight. So we think uh now we
think we're going to get um six was
going to be zero and now we think it's
going to be six and so the new value is
going to be three. So now we have a
better estimate of what C does and that
makes sense. It looked C looked like a
kind of neutral state but it just
brought us to the eight. So we're going
to raise our estimate. Does it make
sense how this is working? We learned
about the state we left based on the
reward we got then and the value of our
landing state. We know that this action
could do something different next time.
So we don't clobber our old value. We
just fold it in. Now you could say that
sounds reasonable, but does folding it
in with a rolling average actually work?
And the answer is under technical
conditions, yes, because the average
gets as alpha gets small enough and and
we could get into that, but this is the
right thing to do in this case. Okay.
All right.
Okay. Let me remove that. Any questions?
Going to talk about its problems and
that's going to lead us to the next
algorithm which is going to be the
critical thing to get through today.
So what do we do? We learned an
algorithm for estimating the value of a
state under a policy uh just by direct
evaluation. It wasn't very good because
it didn't let us take out the
information about where the states go.
This algorithm does. But temporal
difference value learning has some
issues. Okay, it's model free. That's
great. We didn't have to wait and then
estimate a transition function and solve
an MDP. We just averaged everything as
we go as as we went. Um we basically
just did
uh we basically just did I'll just write
it out. Um, basically what this is doing
is it's taking this idea of the value of
a state can be computed by the average
over the landing states of the
transition
that you experience
instantaneous reward plus value of
landing state. Right? It's basically
taking this and replacing this uh
average with a running average. That's
it. Like if you write down this
equation, you cross out the expectation
and replace it with um running average.
That's the algorithm. Okay, that's all
that's going on here. Um but all it does
is policy evaluation. Okay, if we want
to get a policy out of this, this
doesn't tell us how to extract one. So
if you remember, the way we would
extract policies is we would take an
argmax over the actions available to us.
So from a state we would take a max over
all of the actions and then we'd have to
compute the value of each action.
Remember these are called Q states and
their values were Q of SA. We didn't
estimate those. We only estimated the
values. So we're kind of out of luck. Um
and so this uh this leads us to this
idea of maybe we should learn the Q
values instead.
Okay. If we had Q values instead of
values, action selection would be easy.
We would just get into a state. We'd
look at what we've learned about the Q
values exiting that state and we'd pick
the best one or whatever we want to pick
but we would know which one we believe
to be best. Okay. And that makes action
selection model free. The problem with
temporal difference value learning of
any kind is that action selection is
hard. And actually it is worth pointing
out that this is where reinforcement
learning essentially stopped for like
decades because people knew how to do
this. They knew how to evaluate a
policy, but they didn't know how to do
action selection. And the key thing they
didn't know how to do is they didn't
know how to learn about optimal things.
They didn't know how to learn the
optimal values. They only knew how to
learn about the values of the policy
being executed. And maybe that feels
obvious because of course you're going
to learn the values of the policy you're
executing. What other policies values
could you learn by executing pi? And it
turns out that the big breakthrough was
an algorithm called Q-learning which
does two things for you. First of all,
very very mechanically because you have
Q values action selection is easy but it
does something more subtle too which
we'll partly talk about today and then
come back to next time which is
Q-learning allows you to do this amazing
and not obviously possible thing which
is to learn the optimal values following
suboptimal policies.
And the basic idea there is the policy
you're following is really just a way to
see samples. And these Bellman updates
give you the optimal values somehow.
And if there were a way to use the um
the samples we experienced to populate
the Bellman updates, something like
value iteration, that would be great
because then we could learn optimal
things. And it turns out you can't do
that on values, but you can do it on Q
values. All right. So, let's we'll come
back to Q-learning very uh shortly, but
active reinforcement learning requires
you to um we it requires you to take
actions. And next time we'll talk about
whether those actions should be the ones
that look like they're high scoring or
the ones that you've never taken before
or some mix of those and the trade-off
between exploration and exploitation.
We'll come back to that later. But the
point is now we're actually taking
actions. Taking actions is going to be
part of what we do. Um so for full
reinforcement learning what we want to
learn is we want to learn optimal
policies. That means we want to do what
value iteration did. Okay. So we want to
learn not the score we're going to get
from the state if we keep doing pi. We
want to learn the score we're going to
get from the state if we act optimally.
That sounds challenging. How are we
going to do that? We can only take an
average of the things that actually
happen. And so Q-learning uh gives us a
way forward. All right. So again you
don't know the transitions. You don't
know the rewards. You choose the
actions. And we want to learn optimal
things. So just to be clear, we were
learning uh the the values under pi
before and now we'd like to learn the
optimal values. And since no one has
knows how to do that, we're going to
learn the optimal Q values. And that
turns out we would that's better anyway.
Fraction selection. Okay. All right. So
we will come back to this fundamental
trade-off of exploration versus
exploitation. And to emphasize again,
this is not offline planning, even
though we're doing it in the app. Oh,
hey, wait. I got a crawler running back
there.
Okay, crawler's really going. You know,
it turns out in order to learn things,
you have to try things that maybe you
don't know about or maybe you think
they're bad, but you haven't done them
many times. And so, you need to do
something to explore. You need to take
some actions that maybe don't look like
the best thing. And one way to do that,
a bad way, but one way and a way that
you know is is um in the limit going to
do the right thing is to take the best
action you know about and with a certain
probability just do something else. Do a
little bit of uh what's called random
exploration. And you might see this
epsilon here. This is how often random
exploration is happening. So this means
40% of the time it's not taking the
value it knows. So in fact I expect this
is learned quite a lot. So if I turn
this off and I tell it to just take the
action you think is best.
Behold
it lives.
Okay. Now I'll let it keep running.
Let's see if anything happens. Okay. All
right. Back to here.
All
right. So
it turns out that with value iteration,
you just can't do the thing we want. Um
let's remember why. So what was value
iteration? We computed successive
estimates of the value of a state. And
again, this is the optimal value. It's
the value under optimal play. And the
thing we were doing successive estimates
of was increasing depth, more rewards.
It's going to be different now. We're
just going to have improving
approximations. But let's just remember
it at the beginning all our values are
zero because in the case of value
iteration zero rewards means zero sum of
rewards. Okay. And then given some
estimate which before was the next k
steps we would compute a new estimate
which at that in that algorithm was k
plus one steps of rewards. Okay. And it
went like this. Okay. Let's absolutely
make sure we understand this. new
estimate at S
is based on old estimates at next steps.
Okay, so the new estimate at S was a
combination of the instantaneous reward
from the next step and the landing state
S prime's old estimate. All right, well
that's fine. This is what we get from
our samples, right? Every time we take a
sample, we experience a reward. We land
in a state S prime. And that state s
prime has a running estimate that we can
plug in. So we can get this sample just
fine uh whenever we experience a
transition. Great. And because those
transitions are coming in in proportion
to how typical S-prime is, we can defeat
we can sort of replace this weighted
average with just the samples relative
frequencies as we experience them. So we
can get by without knowing t because we
can replace that average weighted by t
with just the empirical sample
contribution to the running average. So
that's great. So like this is no
problem. We know how to get rid of that.
The reason we can't do a sort of
temporal difference style value
iteration is because of the max. Like
the max is just a problem. When we were
following pi, this max was not present
because we were following pi. In order
to make value iteration give the optimal
answers, we can't just average together
the samples for that specific policy, we
have to compare the different actions we
could take. And that's not something we
can do because we only get to execute
one and the one we executed was pi and
we just like this max was just this max
was essentially a brick wall for
reinforcement learning for a long time
because we just we knew the update we
wanted to do. We knew we wanted to do
this value iteration update and we knew
we wanted to do it with a running
average instead of an expectation and no
one had any great ideas about what to do
about the max. There's just no way to
get through it.
What happened was well no one ever found
a way to get through it. But turns out
you don't need it if you work with Q
values. So Q values turn out to be more
useful and not just because you can do
action selection but also when we see
the update we'll see why this was a
breakthrough. So, um, how would we do Q
value iteration? Forget reinforcement
learning. Let's just do a dynamic
program for Q values. The Q value of SA
over the next K plus1 rewards. Well,
let's write it out. What would that be?
If you have K plus one more rewards to
receive and you're in state S and you've
taken action A, well, what's going to
happen? What's that going to be here?
Let me make this an equals.
Well,
you're going to immediately experience
an average. like immediately you're
going to land in some s prime. They'll
be weighted by tsas prime. This is
already looking promising because there
doesn't seem to be a max out here to get
in our way. So we're going to have this
weighted average of what happens in the
next step which is going to be an
instantaneous reward
and it's a Q state. So, we've already
locked down a um there's another Q state
for the other actions
plus the discounted
future optimal
values
except we don't actually know the
optimal values. So, they're going to be
K
except we're not doing value iterations.
They're not going to be V at all. It's
going to have to be Q's. So, what goes
here? Well, it's got to be something
about the Q value for the next K steps
from S prime. We're going to need some
other action from S prime. But which
action should we take?
Well, you should take the best one and
that was basically the revelation that
unlocked the style of reinforcement
learning which is off policy learning.
The idea here is this update works just
as well as value iteration on an MDP
that's known, but it's very different
because now we can still defeat this. We
can get by without t because we can
replace this actual expectation with a
running average in the same style. We'll
do that in the next slide. These are our
samples, right? Um, and that's great.
And when we plug in the future estimate,
instead of plugging in a value under a
fixed policy, we can plug in a Q value
and we plug in a Q value, we make a
choice. Do we want the Q value for this
policy or do we want to put a max in
here? And this max isn't a problem
because it's a max over things we're
actually tracking. We actually track all
the Q values out of every state. And so
we can max them as we go. And if we put
a max there, we will actually learn the
optimal values, not the values of the
policy we are following. This is
actually this is like this is
mind-blowing, right? You can act
randomly. You can fling yourself into
the pit. You can just move however you
like. As long as you get to every state
infinitely often and try every action
inf infinitely often, Q-learning will
let you learn the optimal Q values
regardless of how bad the policy you're
observing is.
That's like
that's that's crazy. Okay. All right.
So, here's Q-learning. We take this
update. It says the new Q value is a
transition weighted average of the
instantaneous reward R plus
the future value which we're going to
compute by maxing over the Q values that
we currently have. And well that's
basically the algorithm. Uh what we
wrote down is essentially the algorithm.
So Q values first let's remember what
they look like. Um there's a Q value not
for every state but for every every
state action pair. And so, for example,
in this state here, um, that's one
state, but it has four Q values, and
we're going to learn them all. Now, one
of them will correspond to the actual
optimal action. The rest are just kind
of sitting there helping us learn, but
we're going to learn them all. Okay? So,
we're going to learn the Q values as we
go. How does that work? We receive a
sample. That's how all reinforcement
learning algorithms start. You were in
S, you took action A, you landed in S
prime, and you received instantaneous
reward R. Well, what are you going to
do? Well, you're going to consider your
running averages. on one hand, well,
first of all, what are we going to learn
about? We were in S and we took action
A. So that's what we're going to learn
about. We're going to land in S prime,
but this doesn't tell us anything about
S prime. It tells us what S and A do.
And we receive reward R, but that only
really tells us about S and A as well.
So we're on one hand, we have an old
estimate of how good we thought SA was.
Okay, we thought this was a good state,
but a poor choice of action or this was
the best action from that state or
whatever it was. We have an old estimate
and we have our new estimate. Our new
estimate is the instantaneous reward R
that we received plus our guess at the
future starting at S prime. That's going
to be a discount plus the value of S
prime. What's the value of S prime?
We're not tracking those. But it's just
the max over A prime of the Q values of
S prime. So if we're thinking about what
happens if we land in the state, well
the value of the state is the max over
all of these Q values. Okay.
All right. So, we have an old estimate.
We have a sample and we're going to play
the same game of put it in a running
average. This is called Q-learning. And
this is essentially what unlocked
reinforcement learning.
Let me show you.
Let me show you this running in an
All right.
Here we're going to have to uh say
bye-bye to the crawler because I have to
shut this one down.
But it learned
it is in
excuse me this
uh this crawler is in fact running
Q-learning. So now you know what it it
does. We'll we'll bring back the crawler
and the Q-learning with uh a
visualization um probably next class.
But let's look at grid world first.
All right. So here is that same running
example we have. Each state is been
broken into its Q values. That is most
states have the actions north,southeast,
and west. And so a Q value for each. The
exit states only have the action exit.
And so it's the Q value for that, which
happens to be the same as the value for
the state when you only have one action.
And we're in this state now. You can see
the blue. And we're going to start
experiencing things. And as we move, so
for example, I'm going to press up.
Okay. And when I went up, what happened?
So, let's actually bring this down for
you so you can see there's some uh
chatter on the back and over here that
says we were starting in state 0. It
took the action north. Um we ended in
state 0 comma 1. We got reward living
reward is zero here apparently negative
0. And um and so what happened? It
looked like we were going to get when I
when I chose north, my old estimate was
zero. I received a zero and I landed in
this state whose Q values are all zero
and therefore whose actual value
estimate the max over those is also
zero. Everything's zero. Nothing
happens. Nothing's going to happen for a
while because there's no living reward
until I transition here. I'm going to go
east. What's going to happen when I go
east? Finally, we're going to learn
still nothing. Why? Because we went from
a state with Q values of zero to another
state with Q values of zero. But what
happens here? I'll choose exit. I'll
look at my Q value of zero
and I will see that my instantaneous
reward is going to be non zero and I'm
going to have to average those together.
I'm going to land in the exits in the
terminal state which has a future value
of zero as well. So you can see what
happens was I got reward one.
Episode one complete. Reward was one.
Now we're beginning episode two. So I
respawn. Okay.
Here the old value was zero. We
experienced a one. And so now it's 0.5
because the learning rate is 1/2. So I
move and nothing's really interesting
until think through what happens when I
go to the east.
Right now, I think East gives a score of
zero under optimal play because that's
the Q value on that side. However, what
I'm going to do is I'm going to
experience an instantaneous reward of
zero and land in a state whose value is
0.5.
I had zero as my current estimate, 0.5
is my new estimate. That means they
should average together and I should see
a 0.25. And there it is. Now, this 0.5
is my current estimate, but I'm about to
receive a one. It's going to look at the
0.5 and the one. and it's going to
average them. I'll get a 0 75. All
right, 0 75 in that corner. It's
converging to the right value. 0.25.
I've managed to learn that if you take
the east action, you land in a good
state. I don't know what the other
actions do because I haven't tried them.
So, we're going to begin episode three.
All right. So, I could keep doing this
for a while. And oh, should have stopped
there. But, uh, you can see here as soon
as I learn I move to here, I got a
little bit of reward here. Um, and
that's because I got a zero
instantaneous reward, but I landed in an
estate that appears to be worth 0.25.
Those other Q values don't matter
because I think it's worth the optimal
one. Um, and so I compare the 0.25 that
I think I'm going to get with the 0 of
my old estimate and I get 0.125. And now
as I move to the right, that 025 is
going to get bigger because now I know I
lead not to five, but I lead to 0 75.
And so I can run this for a while. And
what do you think's going to happen
here? As soon as I move from here to the
east, I'm going to land in a place that
I think gives me 0.12. So, I'm going to
start to see some reward. Okay, there's
my 006. And that 0.12 will get better
because every time I do this, this new
good stuff is replacing
the previous experience. And as soon as
I move here, I'm finally going to get to
see that moving to the north has led me
to a state, which I know to be good
because it led me to states that I know
to be good because they led me to
states. We're using the connectivity,
and we're going to keep learning. Now
notice as I do this, I'm only learning
about the actions I'm taking.
So let's take a bad action and then
we'll see the magic here. I'm going to
move to the south.
That means on this episode, this state
is going to have a bad time. Okay, so
just to be clear, I'm going to go jump
in the cliff and this state which has
been getting me looks like 0.94.
I'm not going to take that action. I'm
going to take this action. Okay. And
then I'm gonna go learn about the pit.
And then I'm going to do it again.
And this is the magic of Q-learning is I
am now learning a couple things. First
of all, I am learning that east is a bad
choice right here. That makes sense.
Okay. But check this out. From this
state, not only is the 0.94
not propagating, not getting worse, it's
not propagating backward. The state
where my mouse cursor is is 0 93.
Because even though I keep jumping into
this pit, I know that there's a 0.94
action
and the fact that there's another action
which is worse, well, I'm not going to
take that one. So the max around the Q
values is preventing this bad experience
from propagating back. If I were
evaluating this policy, it would
propagate back because I wouldn't take
that max. I would just use the one
policy. So that's cool. This bad
experience isn't stopping me from
learning that this top one is good. But
it's better than that because I haven't
even learned that going south is bad
because when I go south I land in a
square which I know there are point
there are three ways to get zero out of.
So the fact that I have been getting 69
doesn't change the fact that I think
south isn't that bad. It's only zero.
And in fact, if I keep coming back up
here, if I do this, I'm going to learn
that even though
I'm going to learn that even though
going